Register of the James Stuart Douglas Miscellaneous Papers, 1922-1935
Hoover Institution Archives
James Stuart Douglas Miscellaneous Papers,
1922-1935
82078
Douglas, James S. (James Stuart), 1868-1949.
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, speeches, resolutions, clippings, and other printed matter, relating to European, especially French, World War I debts to the U.S., and proposals for their reduction or cancellation.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1914-1918--Economic aspects.; World War, 1914-1918--Reparations.; France.; United States--Foreign relations
Biographical Note
1868, June 19 Born, Megantic Township, Quebec, Canada
1891-1909 Assayer and Mine Superintendent, Arizona and Sonora, Mexico
1902 Organized and became President of the Bank of Bisbee, Arizona
1909 President, Bank of Douglas, Arizona
1909 President of the United Verde Extension Mining Company
1913-1914 Vice-president and General Manager of the Cananea Consolidated Copper Company
1917 Head, Section of Stores in France, International Red Cross
1927 Decorated Chevalier of the Legion of Honor (France)
1949, Jan. 2 Died, Quebec, Canada
Series Description
- CORRESPONDENCE, ALPHABETICAL, 1925-1934. (Box Box 1)
  Extensive correspondence with specific individuals, arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Relates almost entirely to European, particularly French, World War I debts to the United States, and proposals for their reduction or cancellation. Includes a few letters neither from nor to James S. Douglas.
- CORRESPONDENCE, CHRONOLOGICAL, 1925-1935. (Box Box 1)
  Less extensive correspondence, relating to the World War I debt reparation issue, arranged chronologically. Also includes a few letters neither from nor to James S. Douglas.
- PRINTED MATTER, 1924-1933. (Box Box 2)
  Clippings, pamphlets, periodical articles, reprints, and other printed material relating to the World War I debt issue, arranged by physical form.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1922-1934. (Box Box 2)
  Reports, memoranda, resolutions, speech transcripts, press releases, notes, miscellany, and other primarily non-printed material, relating predominately to World War I losses and financial reparations. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE, ALPHABETICAL, 1925-1934
  - Andrew, Congressman A. Piatt, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Bacon, Henry Selden, 1926-1933 (Folder 3)
  - Chew, Oswald, 1926-1934 (Folder 4)
  - Delano, Frederic A., 1925-1926 (Folder 5)
  - Mitchell, J.F.B., 1927-1933 (Folder 6)
  - Peabody, Frederick W., 1926-1929 (Folder 7)
  - Snyder, Carl, 1925 (Folder 8)
  - Washington-Lafayette Institution, Inc., 1926-1927 (Folder 9)
  - White, Walter, 1926-1927 (Folder 10)
- CORRESPONDENCE, CHRONOLOGICAL, 1925-1935
  - Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1925
  - 1926 (Folder 12)
  - 1927-1928 (Folder 13)
  - 1929-1935 (Folder 14)
- PRINTED MATTER, 1924-1933
  - Clippings, General (Box 2)
    - n.d. (Folder 1)
    - 1924-1926 July (Folder 2)
    - 1926 August (Folder 3)
    - 1926 September-December (Folder 4)
    - 1927-1928
    - 1931-1933
  - Clippings of articles by or about James S. Douglas
  - Pamphlets, many of which are printed speech transcripts. (Folder 5)
    Arranged alphabetically by author.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1922-1934
  - General (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Beaumarchais, Pierre Augustus (Caron de). Ellinwood, Mr. Beaumarchais, 1925. Typescript study, includes cover letter.
  - Mining
  - War losses. Correspondence with representatives of various U.S. and Allied military departments in an attempt to establish figures for Allied war losses from July 18, 1918 to Nov. 11, 1918. Correspondence dated 1929 Nov.-1930 Feb. (Folder 7)
  - War reparations.
    - General. Resolutions, notes, press releases.
    - Arizona State Legislature, House Joint Memorial 16, Relating to Foreign Trade and Commerce. Published in the Congressional Record, 1933 March 28 (Folder 8)
    - Andrew, A. Piatt, Should the Debt Settlements be Revised? Speech delivered before the American Economic Association, 1927 Dec. 29
    - Conkey, George T., The Cost of the War Fought in Common. Typescript study, includes correspondence arranged chronologically (Folder 9)
    - Hoover, Herbert, Speech given 1922 Oct. Typescript copied from The Commerical and Financial Chronicle of New York, 1922 Oct. 21
    - Houghton, N.D., Public Opinion and the War Debts. Typescript copy, includes cover letter, 1934 March 1
    - Peabody, Frederick W., If America Were France, 1926. Pre-publication copy of a newspaper editorial